let's have a word of Prayer
Heavenly Father lord please whatever
whatever trials challenges we have had
during the week lord I pray at this time
that you would help us to set those
aside and that the word that you have to
speak to us today Lord will be heard and
will be received by this church please
lord please help us to respond in the
way you desire us to respond we pray
this in Jesus name Amen I will let you
know that this this sermon today is to
me a very very serious message and I'm
going to be making an appeal at the end
of this message and I'm not only going
to be making an appeal for those of you
that will respond to come down but after
that appeal for those of you that
respond and come down I want you to come
to the side and I'm going to talk to you
this is not a baptism but it is a very
important appeal and so I will be
speaking with those who respond to this
appeal afterward so just know that this
entire message this entire message today
is leading to an appeal and this message
is crucial for this church guys I am I
don't even know how how to stress how
this message can be pivotal for this
church so I want to pray one more time
and we're going to get into the Word of
God the title of the message house fire
let's pray Heavenly Father bless us Lord
please speak through me lord the things
you have shown me help me to correctly
Express to show
your church that mean that we may
respond Lord please hide me behind your
cross this we pray in Jesus name Amen
I invite you to turn in your Bibles to
the book of Exodus chapter 25 and verse
8 and I want to tell you guys this this
is an exciting message so if you have
any trepidation or any fear that's not
what I want I don't want you to have any
fear no need to be fear to be fearful
this is an exciting message but with
that with this message comes a great
responsibility and that's what makes me
tremble it's how will we respond because
we can do one or two things today we can
we can or we can do a couple of things
we can either say that was a horrible
message hopefully we don't do that the
other thing we could do is we could say
that was a great message and then leave
it at that but the thing that we need to
do is hopefully to save that was a
message from God and yes we need to
respond and that's what I'm hoping what
happened today in Exodus 25 verse 8 -
God tells the children of Israel he
tells Moses he says to him let them do
what make me a sanctuary that I may do
what dwell among them that I may live
among them God instructs Moses to tell
the children of Israel to build a
sanctuary so that his presence could
dwell with them this this sanctuary if I
were to ask you to describe to me the
sanctuary how would you describe it just
from the outward appearance well well ok
let's start let's start with just what
you would say normally the sanctuary
would be what how would you describe it
it was a tent what else you don't have
to give me details I just want a general
description
was it had two compartments very good
what was the purpose of the sanctuary
alright for the Lord's presence to dwell
there so the sanctuary was God's house
was God's what everyone God's house and
because the presence of God was there
the sanctuary was to be treated with
reverence Amen now God makes the
sanctuary and we know that inside the
sanctuary is a presence of God but tell
me about the outer appearance of the
sanctuary it was it was playing some
might even say it was humble yes nothing
on the outside that looked attractive
that looked like oh this is God's house
it was just plain but on the inside
there was the glory and the presence of
God amen in Exodus 25 verse 22 it goes
on to say there that God would put a
murse told them to put a mercy seat
inside the sanctuary which would be a
symbol of God's throne and it says here
there will I meet with thee and I will
commune with thee from above the mercy
seat from between the two cherubim which
are upon the Ark of a testimony of all
things which I give thee in commandment
unto the children of Israel so God
instructed the children of Israel to
make a sanctuary there was to be a
throne in this sanctuary and that throne
was symbolic of God's mercy amen God's
mercy dwelt in this tabernacle it was
his seat if you will
symbolizing that the sanctuary was to be
a house of mercy so the children of
Israel begin to build this sanctuary and
then what we find in Exodus chapter 40
after they have built the sanctuary
Exodus chapter 40 and please notice with
me verses 34 onward Exodus chapter 40
verse 34 it says and they the tabernacle
unto Moses the tent and all his
furniture his taxes his boards his bars
and his pin
and his sockets and jumped down with me
to verse 35 in the Ark of the kharkov
the testimony and the staffs thereof and
the mercy seat let's go down to verse
verse 40 it says uh are we in the right
chapter I'm sorry I'm reading the wrong
chapter Exodus chapter 40 I was reading
verse 39 Exodus chapter 40 verse 34 then
a cloud then a cloud covered the tent of
the congregation and the glory of the
Lord did what fill the tabernacle it
filled the tabernacle say that one time
with me guys a droite fill the
tabernacle now what did the filling of
the tabernacle symbolize God's presence
and where God's presence is there it is
holy amen so the glory of God filled the
tabernacle God's presence is there
signifying this is my house reverence my
house what does it mean that the glory
filled the tabernacle what is the glory
of God what did the glory of God look
like it looked like fire you remember
when God sees when Moses sees the glory
of God Moses describes a glory as a
devouring fire so the glory of God was
the fire of God and the fire of God
filled his temple filled his house it
was a house fire are you with me so far
it was a house fire signifying this is
my house
this is where I dwell this is where I
abide now remember that that the
sanctuary was in the midst of the
children of Israel and the sanctuary was
itself called a tent
tabernacle and that sounds like a humble
name doesn't it where do you live I live
in a tent how many of you would like to
live in a tent no we we want to live in
a house right nobody wants it but God
sets a house in a tent and that tent was
found in the midst of all the tents of
the children of Israel so you had God's
tent and then you had these smaller
tents that surrounded the tabernacle and
the idea was that the people would come
from those tents to the main tent which
was the sanctuary the tabernacle if you
would be so far to say Amen
now this tabernacle this tent was a
moveable notice with me Exodus chapter
40 same chapter and let's look at verse
37 or verse 36 so the Bible says and
when the cloud was taken up from over
the tabernacle the children of Israel
went onward in all their journeys but if
the cloud were not taken up then they
journeyed knocked till the day that it
was taken up for the cloud of the Lord
was upon the tabernacle by day and fire
was appointed by night in the sight of
all the house throughout all their
journeys so this tabernacle was a
moveable tabernacle are you with me so
far
and so when the cloud would moved that
would move the tabernacle would move the
tent would move and this is how God led
the children of Israel now you'll
remember in the New Testament that Jesus
one time goes into the temple and
remember what they were doing in the
temple they were selling all kinds of
things right and jesus said take these
things out because it is written my
father is what house shall be called a
house of prayer so that sanctuary that
tabernacle was to be known as a House of
Prayer and I want you to notice this
notice with me Isaiah chapter 56 Isaiah
chapter 56 verse 6 and 7 Isaiah 56 verse
6 and 7 it says here also the sons of
the strangers who would that be the sons
of the strangers
strangers who would that be the Gentiles
that join themselves to the Lord to
serve Him and to love the name of the
Lord to be his servants everyone that
keepeth the sabbath from polluting it
and taketh hold of my covenant verse 7
even then will I bring to my holy
mountain and make them joyful in my
Watts house of prayer their burnt
offerings and their sacrifices shall be
accepted upon my altar for my house
shall be called a house of prayer for
how many all people
so the sanctuary the tabernacle God said
ultimately it was designed so that even
the Gentiles the strangers would be able
to come to it and it would be a house of
what everyone a house of prayer a house
of prayer so it was a movable house when
the children of Israel were in the
wilderness they had this tabernacle with
them at all times and now you're aware
with the history of the history they
finally get into the Promised Land and
then Israel's start to do some crazy
things like they asked for a what what
did they ask for give us a king now was
it God's will for the children of Israel
to have a king but did he give them a
king yeah in fact God said when they
said you know to Samuel
hey your sons you know aren't acting
right give us a king like the other
nations and then the Bible says that a
grieves Samuel that they had asked us
but God said to Samuel listen they have
not rejected you they have rejected who
me from being King nevertheless listen
to them now does God sometimes work with
our with our craziness God is merciful
sometimes we don't even know what we're
asking for and we ask for it and God
says look it's not the best but because
you asked for it
I'm gonna give it to you sometimes God
has to teach us in these ways you
understand what I'm saying and so and so
the principle I want you to see here is
that sometimes God concedes to what we
want to do God concedes to our desires
knowing that this is not best for you
but your heart is what it's set on it
therefore I'm gonna let you do it and
even in that God will work with you
isn't that crazy
God will actually work with you so God
gives them song and at first saw was a
good King but then he turns out to be a
bad King and obviously we then have a
story of who who comes on the scene as a
new King David and David as a man after
God's own heart but is David perfect no
he's not he's not perfect he is a man
after God's own heart but David makes
his own mistakes yeah okay now I want
you to check this out and um and I'll
come with me to the book of first
Chronicles because now first chronicles
chapter 17 and I'm gonna show you
something here that that is really
really just amazing you may not even see
how amazing this is yet but you will you
will shortly first chronicles are
chapter 17
David settles the kingdom and now you
know he is reigning king and then David
gets an idea did you hear what I just
said
David gets a what everyone and I did
notice with me 1st chronicles chapter 17
and verse 1 now it came to pass as David
sat in his house that David said to
Nathan the Prophet lo I draw on the
house of Cedars but the Ark of the
Covenant of the Lord remains under
Curtin's weight then Nathan said unto
David do all that is that is in thine
heart for God is with thee
pause for a second what is it saying
here what's David thinking what does he
just say hey I'm dwelling in what I'm
dwelling in in this beautiful house but
the Ark of the Covenant is dwelling on
the curtains
what's David thinking here what's he
thinking why should he be in the house
that he's in when the Ark of the
Covenant right when God doesn't have a
house that's what he's thinking and so
he this is where the idea comes from to
build a temple you guys you need to
listen very carefully to this it is
David's idea to build a temple it is
David's idea to build a temple a
structure that does not move a structure
that stays in place now remember the
tent was one it was movable and and the
children of Israel on their journey to
the promised land they moved with a
moveable tent but now David is in is
settled and he says hey wait a minute we
should build a house for God watch this
Nathan says to him in verse 2 then they
think Mason said unto David do all that
is in thine heart for God is with thee
sounds good right but then the next
verse and it came to pass the same night
that the Word of God came to Nathan
saying go and tell David my servant thus
saith the Lord thou shalt not build me
our house to dwell in hold on guys wait
wait a minute
what has God just said like imagine God
you know is up there in heaven and and
David sitting down in this house and
he's like wait a minute I have a great
idea I'm gonna build a house for God and
God is like what hold on and he talked
he says to Nathan Nathan go
Oh David do not build me a house what
did God say do not build me a house hold
on let's find out why let's find out why
Genesis chapter I'm sorry 1st chronicles
chapter 17 verse verse 5 for I have not
dwelt in a house since the day that I
brought up Israel unto this day
but I've gone from tent to tent and from
one tabernacle to another and that's
simply another way of saying look I was
in a movable tent I have not dwelt in a
house since these days would notice what
as he goes on to say and whosoever and
wheresoever I have walked with all
Israel spake I a word to any of the
judges of Israel whom I commanded to
feed my people saying why have you not
built and a house built me a house of
Cedars what is God doing what's he
saying what's he asking what's he saying
the Nathan ok saying to Nathan tell
David hey
did I ask for a house look how long I've
been walking with you guys
have I ever commanded anyone to build me
a house that's what he's saying the
David okay you guys neat this is so
crucial you need to follow this with
everything you have so it says now
therefore verse 7 now therefore thus
shalt thou say unto my servant David
thus saith the Lord of Hosts let me
pause right here let me pause right here
Allan white writes these words she says
David while dwelling in his palace of
cedar felt disturbed in his conscience
as he considered that there was no
suitable dwelling place for the Ark of
God which symbolized his presence it
still rested in the tabernacle which had
been constructed in the wilderness and
borne all the way from Horeb to
Jerusalem in a pilgrimage
for nearly 40 years but now the nation
had ended their pilgrimage and obtained
a permanent location David looked around
him and upon the costly buildings of
cedar the homes of the inhabitants
settled in the good land of Canaan and
conceived the idea that a temple should
be built more worthy for the residence
of God
so who conceived the idea you're sure
about that right so this wasn't God's
idea this is David's idea all right very
good
so far so good so it's interesting
notice with me verse 7 we're gonna read
on here now therefore thus saith thus
shalt thou say unto my servant David
thus saith the Lord of Hosts I took me
from the sheep from the Sheep this is
not a sign that I need glasses
I took thee is that the I took thee from
the sheep coat I just couldn't see that
see wow I took me from the sheep coat
even from following the Sheep that thou
should be ruler over my people Israel
and I have been with thee whither Sarada
has walked and have cut off all thine
enemies from before thee and have made
thee a name like the name of the great
men that are in the earth also I will
ordain a place for my people Israel and
will plant them and they shall dwell in
their place and shall be moved no more
neither shall the children of wickedness
waste them any more as at the beginning
and since that time that I commanded
judges to be over my people Israel
moreover I will subdue all that enemies
furthermore I will tell thee that the
Lord will build V a house ok pause for a
second what has the Lord just told David
he's saying um I don't want you to build
me a house I am going to build you a
house
I'm going to build you ours let's keep
reading and it shall come to pass when
thy days be expired so that means what
after you are after you're dead that
thou must go to be with thy fathers that
I will raise up thy seed after thee
which shall be of thy sons and I will
establish his kingdom he shall build me
a house and I will establish his throne
forever I will be his father and he
shall be my son and I will not take I
will not take my mercy away from him as
I took it from him that was before thee
but I will settle him in my house and in
my kingdom forever and his throne shall
be established for evermore
according to all these words and
according to all this vision so did
Nathan speak unto David so what does God
David he says first I'm going to build
you a house and then what does he say he
says something about David seen and what
does he say your seed will do what will
build a house okay now now so David
hears his news and what does he do how
many of you know what he does after this
what does David think Oh God is gonna
give me a a son right and my son which
turns out to be who Solomon is going to
build my house build a house of God
and so David begins to make plans for
the temple now hold on did God just say
don't build me a house did God just say
do not build me a house because I have
not dwelt in a place that is stationary
y'all not feeling me I have not dwelt in
a place that stationary I've been on the
move don't build me a house but David
his heart is so set on building this
house for God that even after God says
do not build me a house that David
proceeds to do what so he gathers the
material and check this out he begins to
lay out exactly what the tabernacle will
look like now here's something very
interesting when you read about the
instructions Moses God gave to Moses
about the tabernacle it's very detailed
God said do this and do this and do this
and do this and build this and this many
meters and this high and this this is
when you get to this tabernacle that
David and Solomon end the building you
don't find any instructions from God
that's very interesting it's as if God
is saying I didn't ask for a temple but
you want to build me a temple so ok I
will what concede remember give us a
king
well that's it's not best but okay since
your heart is set on it we'll do that
now I know what you're thinking but God
said that Solomon would build him a
house right but but I need you to see
something here because um
in first chronicles chapter 22 first
chronicles chapter 22 the Bible says
this not reading you're hearing then
David said this is the house of the Lord
God by the way partial second did we
just read all the words that God told
Nathan to tell David we read all those
words yes yeah okay notices then David
said this is the house of the Lord God
and this is the altar of the burnt
offering for Israel and David commanded
to get to gather together the strangers
that were in the Land of Israel and he
set Mason's are to hew wrought stone to
build the house of God and David
prepared iron in abundance for the for
the nails for the doors of the gates and
the joinings and the brass in abundance
without wit without weight also the
cedar trees and abundance for the
zidonians and the and they of Tyre
brought much cedar wood to David and
David said Solomon my son is young and
tender and the house that is to be built
for the Lord must be exceeding Magnifico
pause for a second what kind of house is
David want to bill God one that is
exceeding Magnifico that's actually the
word it says in a KJV know it says
magnificent magnificent there magnifico
I want you to build me a house David
says I'm gonna build my house for God
that is so magnificent when you look at
it it's gonna be like my throne let me
ask you a question what kind of house
that God instructed Moses to build him
Moses remember was the word we use
humble you look at the outside Wow
doesn't look like a house that God would
want word well II but there was a
presence of God David won't bill god
this house that is just appealing to the
eyes notice what else
so verse David said Solomon my son is
young and tender the house that has be
built for the Lord must be exceeding
that difficult of Fame and of glory
throughout all countries I will
therefore now make preparations for it
so David prepared abundantly before his
definite something can you sometimes
think you're doing something for God
that God has not commanded and go all
out this I'm gonna do what I'm gonna do
XYZ I'm gonna do it this way in this way
in this way and this is God's plan
because because that's what God wants
verse 6 then he called for Solomon his
son and charged him to build a house for
the Lord God of Israel now check this
out God didn't tell Solomon to build a
house who told Solomon to build the
house did you catch that just now David
tells Solomon to build a house and you
know what I love right now they're just
like hello pastor where is this going
because I'm setting you up I see your
faces I see you like okay follow so God
so David is the one that tells Solomon
to build a house yes now now check this
out keep reading and David said to Saul
um my son asks for me it was in my mind
whose mind my mind to build a house unto
the name of the Lord my God but the word
of the Lord came to me saying thou has
shed blood abundantly and has made great
Wars thou shall not build a house unto
my name because thou has shed much blood
upon the earth in my sight pause for a
second did we read what God told Nathan
to say to David did Nathan say anything
to David about shedding of blood don't
build a house because you said is that
ragazze it okay now let me put this out
here we don't know if God may have said
that or not all we know is that God
didn't tell Nathan that to tell David
are you with me
okay so so this could be that david has
not come up with his own reason
okay well this must be why God doesn't
want me to build a house but then watch
this keep reading
we're in verse verse nine behold this
Murray he's still saying this what God
said behold a son shall be born to thee
who shall be a man of rest and I will
give him rest from all his enemies round
about for his name shall be Solomon and
I will give peace and quietness unto
Israel in his days he shall build a
house for my name and shall be my son
and I will be his father and I will
establish the throne of his kingdom over
Israel forever now my son the Lord be
with thee and prosper thou and build the
house of the Lord thy God as he has said
of thee pause for a second did you hear
in God's discussion with Nathan the name
Solomon you didn't hear the name Solomon
did you what did you hear God said your
seed is going to build my house David
takes that as meaning Solomon your honor
feeling me David understands that as
meaning Solomon so in David's mind check
this out
Solomon is going to be the son of the
heavenly father and and the father will
be his son you get that he will be my
son and I will be his father Solomon is
the one that's going to bring in this
rain of peace Solomon is the one whose
kingdom will last forever Solomon is the
one who will sit upon a throne and his
throne will be a throne of righteousness
in David's mind it's his son Solomon so
in David's mind ah Solomon is going to
build the house of God now remember what
of God do God Caan seeds
he said don't be on the outs and there's
a reason why because this house was to
be built after outward splendor so how
do we know it was in Solomon because the
Bible says that because of Solomon's
sins the kingdom was rent from him so we
know that that these words were not
fulfilled in Solomon God didn't change
his mind what Solomon I was gonna do it
for you but now I'm not
no God didn't change his mind I want you
to check this out see David in his zeal
miss apply the promise of God Luke
chapter 1 verse 26 turn there with me if
you will
Luke chapter 1 verse 26 we're gonna read
through the 33 Luke chapter 1 beginning
with verse 26 notice what the Bible says
in the six month of the angel in the
sixth month the angel Gabriel was sent
from God on to a city of Galilee named
Nazareth to a virgin espoused to a man
whose name was Joseph of the house of
who David and the Virgin's name was Mary
verse 28 the angel came in unto her and
said hail thou art highly favoured the
Lord is with thee blessed art thou among
women let's keep going and when she saw
him she was troubled at his saying and
cast in her mind what manner of
salutation this should be the angel said
unto her fear not Mary that for thou has
found favor with God and behold thou
shalt conceive in thy womb and bring
forth a son and shall call his name
Jesus he shall be great and shall be
called the son of the highest and the
Lord shall give unto him oh wow
I was about to say oh snap but oh wow oh
wow you mean those words weren't talking
about Solomon next verse verse 33 and he
shall reign
over the house of Jacob forever and his
kingdom there shall be no who was God
talking about he was talking about Jesus
the son of David
so Solomon proceeds to build this throne
David's proceeds to gather this material
both failing to understand that the
promise was not talking about Solomon
that's why David named him Solomon
because he heard he will be a man of
peace Shalom so he names him
Solomon thinking he is a fulfillment of
the promise well I want you to check
this out John chapter 2 verse 19 or 21
jesus said destroy this temple and I
will do what I will do what I will build
it again in three days did the son of
David build the temple that son of David
build the temple did the son of David
build the temple according to this verse
alright I want you to notice again for
me Hebrews chapter 1 verse 5 Hebrews
chapter 1 verse 5 notice what the Bible
says here Hebrews chapter 1 verse 5 for
unto which of the Angels said he at any
time thou art my son this day have I
begotten thee and again I will be to him
a father and he shall be to me a son
who is this talking about Solomon or
Jesus does the Bible say in Isaiah
chapter 9 verse 6 and 7 that the
government would be upon his shoulders
come with me to Zechariah chapter 6
Zechariah chapter 6 verse 12 and 13 and
I want you to notice these verses
Zechariah chapter 6 verse 12 and 13
speak unto him saying thus speak of the
Lord of Hosts saying behold the man
whose name is the branch he shall grow
up out of his place and shall build the
temple of the Lord verse 13 even he
shall be
the temple of the Lord and he shall bear
the glory and shall sit and rule upon
his wot throne and he shall be a priest
unto his throne and the counsel of peace
shall be between them both who is the
king that God is talking about that will
sit upon a throne that will rule forever
that will build a temple it is none
other than who Jesus Christ so check
this out
when the children of Israel build this
edifice this temple this this this this
stationary building you find that
ultimately God allows that temple to be
destroyed did you catch that God allows
that temple to be destroyed it is
destroyed by Babylon and then it is
destroyed in 70 AD by the Romans why
does he allow that temple to be
destroyed in fact how many of you
remember when Steven is about to be
stoned and he gives that sermon and he's
talking about this stiff-necked behavior
of Israel do you know what he says right
before the Pharisees the Jews the
Sanhedrin stone him come with me
notice with me Acts chapter 7 verse 44
Acts chapter 7 verse 44 so he's going
through this sermon and then he's Lee
retracing the steps of Israel and then
he says this our fathers had the
tabernacle of witness in the wilderness
as he appointed instructing Moses to
make it according to the pattern that he
had seen which our fathers having
received in it and brought with Joshua
into the land possessed by the Gentiles
whom God drove out before the face of
our fathers onto the date onto the days
of David who found favor before God and
asked to find the dwelling for the God
of Jacob
but Solomon built in my house however
the most high does not dwell in temples
made with hands as a prophet has said
heaven as my throne and earth is my
footstool what house will you build for
me say the Lord or what is the place of
my rest has my hand not made all these
things and then he says you stiff necked
and circumcised
he's basically saying even when God said
don't build me a temple cuz I can't
dwell in these things they said now
we're gonna build you a temple so now
all of that was a setup I know a long
setup but you need to check this out
guys because what happens when Jesus
dies what happens in the temple the veil
in the temple is rent meaning that what
the presence of God is no longer in that
temple are you with me
it wasn't there in the first place it
was there by Jesus himself being in that
temple for for a moment but the it's
showing Israel look I don't dwell in the
temple anymore that was not my plan so
now what now how is God going to dwell
with his people where is he going to
dwell and some of you are thinking are
the heavenly temple pastor and I say
amen amen but that's not the answer I'm
looking for and you go here I know I
know in our hearts and I would also say
amen to that too
but that's not the answer I'm looking
for because check out what God does come
with me to the book of Acts chapter 2
our chapter two and let's begin reading
from verse 1 Acts chapter 2 at verse 1
and when the day of Pentecost was fully
come they were all with one Accord and
in what's one place and suddenly there
came a sound from heaven as a rushing
mighty wind and it filled what did it
filled what did it fill all the what all
the house pause for a second let me come
down here for this where did the spirit
fall where did it fall heavenly father
set our minds up for this right now
help us to receive this Lord in Jesus
name Amen
where did the spirit fall okay pause in
Exodus 40 where does the Spirit of God
fall what does it feel in Exodus 40 what
does it feel it filled after the temple
is built and then they finish all the
temple then the glory of God
the Spirit of God the presence of God
filled the tabernacle to demonstrate
that this is where God dwells this is
where God's power is this is God's house
when Jesus dies the veil in the temple
is rent in - God is saying I don't dwell
here anymore well God where is your fire
now where is your fire now and where
does God pour out his fire
you know what in a house in a house in a
house you ever think about whose house
that was what was your house how would
you feel about the Spirit of God falling
in your home would that change your
house forever that would that make your
house holy ground where does God pour
out his spirit in the New Testament
where is his new house beloved his new
house is your house okay no no no no no
no no no no don't think oh my body's a
temple no no no no no no no yes yes yes
yes get that but that's not what I'm
talking about right now God pours out
his spirit in a house his church was in
a house God begins his movement in our
house some Bach was willing to open
their house up to disciples who came
into that house and prayed and God says
I'm doing something new my spirit is now
going to be manifested in our house in
homes Yana the start of the early church
church was not in a structure
it was an out it was a small group Wow
you made me work for that the spirit
poured out in a house a small group of
people meeting together and God says
listen I no longer do you don't have to
come to the tabernacle to meet me any
longer now I'm sending a new sign I can
be met in your home hold on guys
the early church in the Old Testament
the church had its beginning with the
sanctuary in the New Testament the
church had its beginning in somebody's
house and the glory of God fell in that
house how many of you were in those days
would have opened up your house for the
possibility of that meeting of the
twelve disciples well you know I'm busy
I got work to do I can't open up my
house to strangers hold on so check this
out it says it filled all the house
where they were sitting it filled all
the what everyone house where they were
sitting now remember this what did Jesus
say about yourselves my father's house
shall be called a house of what treasure
so hold on wait a minute if Pastor what
you're telling me then is that the early
church had its beginning in a house and
that house was a house of prayer now
what we think of we think of house of
prayer what we think of we think of
worship is we think come to church look
at this beautiful structure guys look
isn't it beautiful look at the glass
church look at the lights these are
special lights lights for the glory of
God
yes this is what church is look at the
pews look at the carpet look how
beautiful this is God aren't you
impressed
God says you call this church I didn't
pour out my spirit in a building I
poured out my spirit in a house I poured
out my spirit guys in a house so not
what we find is that an axe chapter 2
the house fire is the house fire in the
Old Testament the house fire was a
sanctuary but in the New Testament the
house fire is on the day of Pentecost
and now God said take that fire and I
want you to go two by two into other
houses and spread the house fire why do
you think the church grew so rapidly
it's because they were following God's
plan house fires house fires and all
these house fires started popping up all
over Jerusalem and that's why the gospel
was so rapidly spread to Jerusalem
because they were meeting in these small
groups they were breaking bread together
how often daily going from what house to
house spreading fires beloved this is
absolutely mind-blowing to me but but
there is something more that you need to
see because you see what God is doing
he's just saying that
now that look in the Old Testament they
came to the sanctuary to see me in the
New Testament I want you to take me to
see them now the glory of God has moved
from the from the big tent into the
small tents and that's how the gospel
was supposed to get into all the world
in other words beloved let me say
plainly God needs your house it's not
enough to say hey you know what well god
I don't want you
my house so we're gonna build you a
house and I'm not saying that's what
happened here or what's happened here or
what's happened in any other church but
what I'm saying is could it be that we
have gotten away from the New Testament
model of house fires you see beloved in
the New Testament because they were
meeting in homes they knew each other
they knew each other on a personal level
they really knew what it was to
fellowship with one another it was no
more well I don't know yeah I've been
coming to church for 15 years and we've
never spoken
that didn't happen back then why because
everyone knew everybody else why because
they could not set up these huge
churches because they were being
persecuted
so the churches had to be in-house and
the gospel spread from house to house
you remember when Saul goes looking for
the church to pursue the church where
did he go
the Bible says he went house-to-house
looking for the church beloved when you
read stuff like this the church in
Philippi or the church in a guess what
they're not talking about this they were
talking about something that was going
on in somebody's house I know we're
getting uncomfortable right now
because you know what the appeal is
right you know the appeal that's coming
and it's not even appeal time and the
worst thing about it is even if you're
just visiting
you know what the appeal is going to be
for your house when you go back to where
you're from you know and there's that
challenge now my house yeah God wants
your house he wants your house because
beloved listen in your house you can
make friends with people that you can't
really do in this house do you know how
it is we come to church Sabbath after
South hey hello happy Sabbath I don't
really like you
[Laughter]
that can't happen in house meetings
because you're too up close and personal
your sound what I'm saying you're too up
close and personal you begin to share
things that are personal in a way that
you would never share anybody going
through struggles happy Sabbath
everything is fine you're not gonna do
that here but guess where you would do
it yeah you would do it in the house
where ten of you are meeting we're 15 of
you're meeting what you've gone to know
each other so well that you're like you
know what I've really been having this
struggle I hate brother so annoyed
Church I'm not getting along with my
family I'm struggling with with this
thing or that thing because you not have
a people that you trust and that's what
what's happening people were going from
house to house this was a New Testament
model and this is how our beloved the
church was growing so rapidly there were
no central places of worship now Daniel
7:25 the Bible speaks of this little
horn power that would think to change
times and laws I want you to imagine all
these house fires these house fires that
are going on and the devil is looking
down on this house fires is saying this
this is dangerous stuff their meaning in
homes their meaning in small groups and
and and the gospel is spreading more
rapidly we cannot contain the fire so
we've got to do something and so you
understand that that in the book of
Revelation there's this prophecy of
these seven churches the first is
Ephesus the second is Smyrna
representing the persecuted Church and
then the third church is pergamus now
it's the pergamus period that represents
a period of time it's the pergamus
period in which a man by the name of
Constantine comes on the scene and
Constantine you remember he converts to
what to Christianity and when he
converts to Christianity he stops the
persecution of the churches so remember
those small groups that had to be
meeting in homes
because of the persecution that
basically almost overnight went away
because you know what Constance started
doing they started building started
building
come with me to Romans revelation and I
need to show you this Revelation chapter
2 Revelation chapter 2 and and verse 12
to the Angel of the church in Pergamos
write these things saith he which has
the sharp sword with the two edges I
know thy works and where thou dwellest
even where Satan's seat is and ah-has
hold thou holdest fast my name and has
not denied my faith even the days of
wearing Antipas my faithful martyr who
was my faithful martyr who was slain
among you where Satan dwelleth that word
for seat what Satan's seat is it's the
word thrown off Satan's throne what time
period is this perilous time period it's
a time period of Constantine and I'm
giving you like a super fast Bible Bible
study and prophecy so just please take
my word for it this is common you know
knowledge amongst us the Pergamus period
represents the time where Constantine
basically brought in this compromise
with the church and in this prophecy the
Bible says I know where Satan's seat is
where his throne is remember in the old
days when God made the sanctuary did he
set up a throne did he set up a throne
in the sanctuary
it was his mercy seat that's where the
presence of God dwelt in the New
Testament where is a throne of God
where has his presence been poured out
in the houses my throne my mercy is in
houses so I want you to go from house to
house and I want you to set up my throne
in these houses when Constantine comes
along he says we're gonna build in fact
the church the Church of the Dark Ages
says we're going to build structures I
want you to check this out guys a
cathedral you know the cathedral is yeah
a cathedral is Latin for chair or
bishops throne that's what the word
Cathedral means the bishops throne a
seat I know where Satan's seat dwells
the setting up of cathedrals and
basilica's and these massive temples
where people now stop doing the small
group the house house and began coming
we're now the pastor becomes the center
of worship it was no longer about small
groups and let's meet here and there and
and and you know we're gonna be
preaching amongst ourselves and when
Paul can come by know now it became well
we've got these edifices now it moved
from a focus on Jesus to a focus on well
how shall we worship in these gigantic
buildings what is the right way what is
the structure shall we have Sabbath
school at 9:00 or 9:30 sacrilege you
know thats our school starts at 9:30
check out Exodus chapter 15 for Sabbath
school yeah check this out what one
source said it says it like this one
source it this way
churches once instant intimate became
institutionalized policy took precedence
over people and meetings became more
important than ministry instead of the
church being a place where loneliness
ended it became the place where
loneliness began in the home church
environment people were expected to
participate but in the large
congregation atmosphere the flocks
scattered in small group structures
people could speak and share the word
with boldness but this became impossible
in large gatherings the whole church
became swallowed up with the arrival of
bricks and mortar and
began the slow death of the vibrant
church it did not take long before all
preaching or public speaking was
centered in the pulpit choirs took over
the simple singing of fellowship while
members learn the great Christian art of
spectatorship before long they also
learned how to be bumps on the church
log Wow guys have we been set up
have we been set up to change the way
that we view church so that we view
church in such a way that ultimately
will lead to the church going nowhere
stationary structure God we know we're
gonna do instead of these small houses I
mean that's just so meager small green
let's build you a great Athens edifis
and we'll do worship this way and we'll
we'll be concerned about liturgy and how
and what's the right way and what's the
right time and all but love it they
didn't have any of those instructions in
the early church and yet the early
church grew way more rapidly than we are
growing right now
while the while the church started
building these emphases you know where
the true church was and they were in the
wilderness they were still mean in small
groups
you guys have we strayed from the
pattern that God has demonstrated to us
in the scripture the answer is yes and
the question is what are we going to do
about it what are we here at Campbell
going to do are we going to say oh very
informative sermon on to next week or is
that we gonna do because beloved I can
tell you right now I am I am tired of
preaching to the choir there is no
reason you guys are saved in Christ what
reason do you have to not be doing the
will of God in seeking and saving the
Lost we act as if our entire
responsibility is to come to church and
critique the sermon let's see how you do
this week pastor that's not what
Christianity is about that's not what
God called you to do I'm getting ready
to close beloved but but I need you to
catch the importance of this point the
early church of the church during the
Dark Ages kept meeting in small groups
and when the Reformation took place you
know what happened the Reformers they
they address a lot of issues but this is
one that they did not address so check
this out
when the Adventist Church came on the
scene what do you think what do you
think our pioneers what principle do you
think our pioneers here let me just read
it to you spirit of prophecy here's what
it says in our churches let companies be
formed for service
lett different ones unite in labor as
fishers of men
let them seek to gather Souls from the
corruption of the world into the saving
purity of Christ love the Church of
Christ on earth was organized for
missionary purposes and the Lord desires
to see the entire church devising ways
and means whereby high and low rich and
poor may hear the message of truth if
there is a large number in the church
let the members be formed into small
companies small groups guys let the
members be formed into small companies
to work not only for church members but
for unbelievers if one if in one place
there are only two or three who know the
truth let them form themselves into a
band of workers do you realize that this
is the model that our church was based
upon and then after Ellen White died
guess what we started to do
let's build churches big churches and
with these big churches we'll just
gather all the people in that we can and
we left the model that Ellen White said
we should be following and beloved if
you want to know why if you look at the
rate of growth in the Adventist Church
when we were doing this versus the rate
of growth now it is night and day we
stopped the fire there are no more house
fires that's the problem because when
their house fires
each one of us bears a responsibility to
help that fire burn here you can sit
back and be like I'll let them let the
pastor preach Oh what there's 20 50
people in here that usually do
everything let them do it you can't do
that in a small group all hands are
required to be on deck so when God says
the church in San Jose he's not talking
about five churches what he wants to see
is hundreds of churches your house as a
church and your house as a church and
your
as a church and then on Sabbath yes we
can all come together and praise God
together but during the week we are
fellowshipping okay guys my sermons done
but the question is very simple what are
we going to do with this what are we
going to do with this we can either be
like wow that was great and move on or
we can say all right we're about to
start some fire in San Jose and beloved
I'm tired of just playing with fire it's
time to start house fires so here's my
appeal right now my appeal is this God
is looking for people who will give
their homes for a house fire yeah that
means a pastor I'm gonna open up my
house for a small group I don't think I
can teach it but if you can get someone
to teach it if you if we can find
someone to teach it I will open my house
up for small groups and we are starting
this not next month not next year we're
gonna be starting this like now like now
wait pastor but how are we gonna do this
we don't know what to do guess what the
early church got their instructions from
the Holy Spirit
don't worry about what to do worry about
the Lord having your heart to do it so
here's my appeal I'm down here my house
is open so God has one house does anyone
want to join me
yeah remember I'm going to be talking to
you guys afterward if you're saying Lord
use me I want I will give my house set
my house on fire
I know you're struggling right now guys
I know and you know what listen even if
you're not from here disappeared is for
you go back home to your home churches
I'm not putting anyone on the spot but
don't feel like yeah this is you know
I'm not hearing Campbell who this is for
all of us
Here I am Lord here's my house I'm
willing use me remember guys you don't
have to teach all I'm asking you is you
for you to give your house to the Lord
because it is sacred and holy ground
that is where the church is
and I'm gonna wait on this one you can
eat some relax
this is serious guys
okay don't mix these groups up so you
are the ones that are standing because
you're saying use my house and I don't
know how many houses we have here right
now but praise God because it looks like
we have some house fires that are about
to get started
and for that I am totally stoked I am
totally excited now now this is another
appeal and it's this alright I don't
feel like opening my house because you
know my house has emit whatever but
you're saying I'm going to be in one of
those house fires I will be there I
would like for you to stand you will not
have to stay by but I do want you to
stand I will be there I'm gonna be a
part I'm going to help these fires grow
so you guys who have stood and said all
over my house I want you to look around
to see those who have their hands raised
look around those who are standing
saying I'll be part of the fire please
raise your hand and keep them up raise
your hand and keep them up raise your
hand and keep them I want you to look
around and I want you to see these are
the ones that you can go to and say hey
will you be in my group will you be in
my home hopefully they live near to you
alright
now I'm gonna ask what no no no I'm not
gonna ask anymore I don't want to push
anything I'm gonna stop it right here
you guys I want you to look around and I
want you to see what's going on because
we're about to do something new here
we're about to stop playing Church
because this what we've been doing is
playing Church we're about to do real
church we're about to do church after
the acts to model that's what church is
I'm not putting down us getting together
on please understand we we praise God
this is the day that the Lord has made
amen
but we're about to do church we're about
to do church we are about to do church
Heavenly Father
we've seen some things today that have
moved us to understand why we are not
growing the way that we should
father we have seen that Satan has let
out of his mouth water as a flood in
order to put out house fires Lord today
there are those who are standing who
have said here is my house use it Lord
according to your will and so though we
are praying for the dedication of these
homes in which small groups are going to
begin to meet and those fires are going
to begin to burn so Lord send your
spirit there to these homes even now and
then Lord for those that have stood
saying I will be a part of that fire
building process I pray Lord I pray Lord
that you would use them in a mighty way
and then Lord I pray for those of us who
may be struggling with this message who
may just feel like this is the way we do
Church this is how we have always done
it and this is how we will continue to
do it Lord I pray that you will remind
us of David who went all out when you
did not command him to do so help us
Lord to know that we're following your
voice and not moving on our own will on
our own plans Lord father forgive us
forgive us as a world church Lord for
often being so cold in our fellowship
like we don't know each other like we're
strangers and that's what that that is
it we don't know each other
Lord Satan has has attempted to set us
up to fail
so Lord we're asking here that in this
church you will begin the fires that you
will begin to set our homes on fire that
your spirit will be poured out in our
houses and that we will begin to see
that fire move from house to house from
tent to tent turn this place upside down
Lord and may this be Lord the beginning
of your fire burning here in this city
this we pray in jesus name amen and amen
I'm gonna ask those of you standing you
know who you are please after this
closing song I'm gonna ask you to meet
me right up front right here I want to
talk to you just for a few minutes and
then I will dismiss you